<edge-cases>

  <meta>
    <version>2.0</version>
    <last-updated>2025-10-15</last-updated>
    <purpose>
      Defines Brain’s unified policy for handling abnormal or boundary scenarios (edge cases) across agents and systems.
      Ensures graceful degradation, system stability, and predictable recovery under non-standard conditions.
    </purpose>
  </meta>

  <classification>
    <type id="data">
      <trigger>Malformed, missing, or conflicting data input.</trigger>
      <response>Validate structure, sanitize values, and request resubmission if unrecoverable.</response>
      <validation>Ensure recovered dataset passes integrity checks before reuse.</validation>
      <fallback>Quarantine corrupted data and notify Architect Agent for manual review.</fallback>
    </type>

    <type id="logic">
      <trigger>Contradictory reasoning output or circular dependency detected.</trigger>
      <response>Re-run reasoning cycle under stricter constraints with reduced inference depth.</response>
      <validation>Verify logical consistency score ≥ 0.9 after correction.</validation>
      <fallback>Escalate to Architect Agent and freeze offending reasoning thread.</fallback>
    </type>

    <type id="resource">
      <trigger>Exceeded token, memory, or CPU threshold defined in core-constraints.xml.</trigger>
      <response>Gracefully halt task and commit partial progress snapshot.</response>
      <validation>Ensure task resumed under reduced load and identical input context.</validation>
      <fallback>Defer to Brain scheduler for deferred execution in low-load window.</fallback>
    </type>

    <type id="network">
      <trigger>Timeout, dropped connection, or inconsistent API response.</trigger>
      <response>Retry request up to 3 times with exponential backoff.</response>
      <validation>Confirm identical checksum between retried and initial request.</validation>
      <fallback>Failover to cached replica or alternative endpoint.</fallback>
    </type>

    <type id="unknown">
      <trigger>Unhandled behavior or undefined exception detected.</trigger>
      <response>Invoke correction-protocol-enforcement.xml for diagnostic re-evaluation.</response>
      <validation>Ensure system remains responsive and state integrity preserved.</validation>
      <fallback>Enter safe-mode and isolate agent until root cause identified.</fallback>
    </type>
  </classification>

  <validation>
    <criterion>All edge-case responses must complete within 3 retries or escalate.</criterion>
    <criterion>System uptime must remain ≥ 0.99 during recovery cycles.</criterion>
    <criterion>Edge-case recurrence rate ≤ 0.02 per 1000 executions.</criterion>
  </validation>

  <escalation>
    <path id="standard">Notify Architect Agent → Log to edge_case_audit.log → Resume operations.</path>
    <path id="critical">Suspend affected agent → Trigger rollback → Alert Brain Core.</path>
  </escalation>

  <integration>
    <link>core-constraints.xml</link>
    <link>error-recovery.xml</link>
    <link>correction-protocol-enforcement.xml</link>
    <link>quality-gates.xml</link>
  </integration>

  <meta-controls>
    <compactness>Structured XML for automated CI testing and resilience simulation.</compactness>
    <logging>All edge-case activations recorded in edge_case_audit.log with type, severity, and resolution time.</logging>
    <governance>Architect Agent reviews recurring edge-case patterns and updates policies quarterly.</governance>
  </meta-controls>

</edge-cases>

